SPENCER FREI

Assistant Professor, UC Davis

spencerfrei.github.io

sfrei@ucdavis.edu

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests are in the foundations of deep learning and artificial intelligence. My goal is to understand the statistical and computational mechanisms underlying the success of deep learning and AI, with the aim of improving the performance of systems utilizing these technologies. Areas of interest include generalization theory for neural networks (including 'benign overfitting'), implicit regularization of optimization algorithms, and large language models.

EMPLOYMENT

Tenure-track Assistant Professor, Department of Statistics, University of California, Davis

2023-present

Postdoctoral Fellow, Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing, UC Berkeley

2021-2023

- Mentors: Peter Bartlett and Bin Yu.
- Part of the NSF/Simons Collaboration on the Theoretical Foundations of Deep Learning.
- Visitor at École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), Sep. & Oct. 2022, hosted by Emmanuel Abbé.

EDUCATION

Ph.D, Statistics, UCLA

2015-2021

— Co-advisors: Quanquan Gu and Ying Nian Wu; committee members: Arash Amini and Qing Zhou.

MSc., Mathematics, University of British Columbia, Vancouver

2013-2015

— Advisor: Edwin A. Perkins.

BSc., Mathematics, McGill University, Montréal

2009-2013

— First class honours.

PUBLICATIONS AND PREPRINTS

- 1. Neil Mallinar*, Austin Zane*, **Spencer Frei**, Bin Yu. Minimum-norm interpolation under covariate shift. *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*, 2024.
- 2. Ruiqi Zhang, **Spencer Frei**, Peter L. Bartlett. Trained transformers learn linear models in-context. *Journal of Machine Learning Research* 25(49), 2024.
- 3. Zhiwei Xu, Yutong Wang, **Spencer Frei**, Gal Vardi, Wei Hu. Benign overfitting and grokking in ReLU networks for XOR cluster data. *International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)*, 2024.
- 4. **Spencer Frei***, Gal Vardi*, Peter L. Bartlett, Nathan Srebro. The double-edged sword of implicit bias: Generalization vs. robustness in ReLU networks. *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems* (NeurIPS), 2023.
- Spencer Frei*, Gal Vardi*, Peter L. Bartlett, Nathan Srebro. Benign overfitting in linear classifiers and leaky ReLU networks from KKT conditions for margin maximization. Conference on Learning Theory (COLT), 2023.
- 6. **Spencer Frei***, Gal Vardi*, Peter L. Bartlett, Nathan Srebro, Wei Hu. Implicit bias in leaky ReLU networks trained on high-dimensional data. *International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)*, 2023. (Spotlight)
- 7. **Spencer Frei**, Niladri Chatterji, Peter L. Bartlett. Random feature amplification: Feature learning and generalization in neural networks. *Journal of Machine Learning Research* 24(303), 2023.

- 8. **Spencer Frei**, Niladri Chatterji, Peter L. Bartlett. Benign overfitting without linearity: Neural network classifiers trained by gradient descent for noisy linear data. *Conference on Learning Theory (COLT)*, 2022.
- 9. **Spencer Frei***, Difan Zou*, Zixiang Chen*, Quanquan Gu. Self-training converts weak learners to strong learners in mixture models. *International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS)*, 2022.
- 10. **Spencer Frei** and Quanquan Gu. Proxy convexity: A unified framework for the analysis of neural networks trained by gradient descent. *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)*, 2021.
- 11. Difan Zou*, **Spencer Frei***, Quanquan Gu. Provable robustness of adversarial training for learning halfspaces with noise. *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*, 2021.
- 12. **Spencer Frei**, Yuan Cao, Quanquan Gu. Provable generalization of SGD-trained neural networks of any width in the presence of adversarial label noise. *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*, 2021.
- 13. **Spencer Frei**, Yuan Cao, Quanquan Gu. Agnostic learning of halfspaces with gradient descent via soft margins. *International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)*, 2021. **(Long Talk)**
- 14. **Spencer Frei**, Yuan Cao, Quanquan Gu. Agnostic learning of a single neuron with gradient descent. *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)*, 2020.
- 15. Ariana E. Anderson, Mirella Diaz-Santos, **Spencer Frei** *et al.* Hemodynamic latency is associated with reduced intelligence across the lifespan: an fMRI DCM study of aging, cerebrovascular integrity, and cognitive ability. *Brain Structure and Function*, 2020.
- 16. **Spencer Frei**, Yuan Cao, Quanquan Gu. Algorithm-dependent generalization bounds for overparameterized deep residual networks. *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)*, 2019.
- 17. **Spencer Frei** and Edwin Perkins. A lower bound for p_c in range-R bond percolation in two and three dimensions. *Electronic Journal of Probability* 21(56), 2016.
- 18. **Spencer Frei**, Kathryn Lockwood, Greg Stewart, Justin Boyer, Burt S. Tilley, On thermal resistance in concentric residential geothermal heat exchangers. *Journal of Engineering Mathematics* 86(1), 2014.

Preprints

• Nikhil Ghosh, **Spencer Frei**, Wooseok Ha, Bin Yu. The effect of SGD batch size on autoencoder learning: Sparsity, sharpness and feature learning. *Preprint* (under review), arXiv:2308.03215.

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

Applied Scientist Intern, Amazon Alexa AI, Cambridge, MA

Summer 2020

— Worked on natural language understanding using Transformer-based multilingual language models.

Student Researcher, Chatterbaby/UCLA School of Medicine, Los Angeles, CA

2018-2020

— Developed deep learning models for audio analysis of infant cries that were deployed in Chatterbaby app (100k+ downloads on Android). Employed 20 hr/week when not teaching.

Biostatistical Consultant, Ritter Pharmaceuticals, Los Angeles, CA

2017-2019

— Consulted on the analysis of clinical trial data using linear regression and mixed effects models.

Student Researcher, Blackthorn Therapeutics/UCLA School of Medicine, Los Angeles, CA 2016–2018

 Analyzed MRI and neuropsychiatric data using generalized linear models for a biotech company-sponsored project. Employed 20 hr/week when not teaching.

^{*} indicates equal contribution.

HONORS

- Selected for NeurIPS 2023 Tutorial, "Reconsidering Overfitting in the Age of Overparameterized Models"
- Rising Star in Machine Learning, University of Maryland, 2022.
- Best Reviewer Award: ICML 2020, ICML 2021, NeurIPS 2021, ICLR 2022.
- Dissertation Year Fellowship, UCLA, 2020–2021.
- Most Promising Computational Statistician, UCLA, 2016.
- Research Fellowship, Montréal Institut des sciences mathématiques, 2012.

TALKS

$^{\vee}$ indicates virtual presentation

 "Reconsidering Overfitting in the Age of Overparameterized Models" (three hour tutorial) NeurIPS 2023 Tutorial, presented with Vidya Muthukumar and Fanny Yang 	December 2023
 "Learning Linear Models In-Context with Transformers" UCLA, Department of Statistics and Data Science Seminar École normale supérieure, INRIA SIERRA Seminar Sorbonne Université and Paris Diderot University, Statistics Seminar Apple Machine Learning Research, Cupertino University of Basel, Department of Mathematics and Computer Science Seminar University of Oxford, Computational Statistics and Machine Learning Seminar University of Cambridge, Machine Learning Group Google DeepMind, London Imperial College London, Imperial + AI Seminar The Alan Turing Institute, London, Rough Paths Interest Group\(^\text{V}\) Stanford University, Tengyu Ma group meeting Google Research, In-Context Learning Reading Group\(^\text{V}\) 	May 2024 April 2024 April 2024 November 2023 November 2023 October 2023 October 2023 October 2023 October 2023 October 2023 September 2023 August 2023
 "Benign Overfitting from KKT Conditions for Margin Maximization" Conference on Learning Theory, Bangalore 	July 2023
 "Implicit Regularization and Benign Overfitting for Neural Networks in High Dimensions" Youth in High Dimensions Workshop, International Center for Theoretical Physics, Trieste UC Berkeley, Department of Biostatistics Seminar University of British Columbia, Mathematics of Information, Learning, and Data Seminar University of Alberta, Dept. of Mathematical and Statistical Sciences, Statistics Seminar EPFL, Fundamentals of Learning and Artificial Intelligence Seminar 	May 2023 April 2023 January 2023 October 2022 September 2022
 "Statistical Learning Theory, Optimization, and Neural Networks" (two hour tutorial) — Simons Institute, Deep Learning Theory Workshop & Summer School 	August 2022
 "Benign Overfitting without Linearity" University of Southern California, Symposium on Frontiers of Machine Learning and AI Joint Statistical Meetings, Washington, D.C. Conference on Learning Theory, London ETH Zürich, Data, Algorithms, Combinatorics, & Optimization Seminar Harvard University, Probabilitas Seminar University of Toronto, Statistics Research Day University of British Columbia, Christos Thrampoulidis group meeting Theory of Overparameterized Machine Learning Workshop Google Research, Algorithms Seminar Oxford University, Yee Whye Teh group meeting NSF/Simons Mathematics of Deep Learning Seminar 	November 2022 August 2022 July 2022 June 2022 May 2022 April 2022 April 2022 April 2022 March 2022 March 2022 March 2022 March 2022

• "Random Feature Amplification: Feature Learning and Generalization in Neural Networks"

— EPFL, Nicolas Flammarion group meeting
 — Microsoft Research, Machine Learning Foundations Seminar[∨]
 — Columbia University, Daniel Hsu group meeting[∨]
 — Theory of Overparameterized Machine Learning Workshop[∨]
 April 2022
 April 2022

• "Self-Training Converts Weak Learners to Strong Learners in Mixture Models"

— Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing, Deep Learning Theory Symposium December 2021

• "Proxy Convexity: A Unified Optimization Framework For Neural Networks Trained by Gradient Descent"

— Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing, Meet the Fellows Welcome Event September 2021

• "Generalization of SGD-Trained Neural Networks in the Presence of Adversarial Label Noise"

— ETH Zürich, Young Data Science Researchers Seminar

April 2021

— Johns Hopkins University, Machine Learning Seminar

April 2021

— Max-Planck-Institute MiS, Machine Learning Seminar

March 2021

— NSF/Simons Mathematics of Deep Learning Seminar

February 2021

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

- Workshop co-organizer: Deep Learning Theory Workshop & Summer School, Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing, Berkeley, 2022.
- Area Chair/Senior PC for conferences: NeurIPS 2023, ALT 2024, NeurIPS 2024.
- Area Chair for workshops: Theoretical Foundations of Foundation Models @ ICML 2024.
- Reviewer for journals: Annals of Statistics, Journal of Machine Learning Research, SIAM Journal on Mathematics of Data Science, Neural Computation, Mathematics of Operations Research, Transactions on Machine Learning Research.
- Reviewer for conferences: ICML 2020, NeurIPS 2020, AISTATS 2021, ICML 2021, NeurIPS 2021, ICLR 2022, AISTATS 2022, ICML 2022, ICLR 2023, COLT 2023.
- Reviewer for workshops: Theory of Overparameterized Machine Learning (TOPML) 2021, ICML Workshop on Overparameterization: Pitfalls & Opportunities (ICMLOPPO) 2021, TOPML 2022, NeurIPS Workshop on Mathematics of Modern Machine Learning (M3L) 2023, NeurIPS Workshop on Robustness of Few-Shot Learning in Foundation Models (R0-FoMo) 2023.
- Reviewer, ENVISION Research Competition for Women in STEM, 2022.
- Volunteer for Queer in AI.

UNIVERSITY SERVICE

- UC Davis
- Department of Statistics, Publicity and Event Planning committee, 2023-2024
- Department of Statistics, Seminar organizer, Winter 2024

CONFERENCE, WORKSHOP, AND PROGRAM PARTICIPATION

- Modern Paradigms in Generalization Program (Long-term Participant), Simons Institute, Berkeley, 2024.
- International Conference on Learning Representations. Vienna, 2024.
- Neural Information Processing Systems. New Orleans, 2023.
- Conference on Learning Theory. Bangalore, 2023.
- Youth in High Dimensions. Trieste, 2023.
- Joint Statistical Meetings. Washington, DC, 2022.
- Deep Learning Theory Summer Cluster. Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing, Berkeley, 2022.
- Conference on Learning Theory. London, 2022.
- Deep Learning Theory Symposium. Simons Institute for the Theory of Computing, Berkeley, 2021.
- Mathematical/Scientific Foundations of Deep Learning Annual Meeting. Simons Foundation, New York, 2021.

- ICML Workshop on Overparameterization: Pitfalls and Opportunities. Online, 2021.
- Theory of Overparameterized Machine Learning (TOPML) Workshop. Rice University (online), 2021; 2022.
- Theory of Deep Learning Special Quarter. TTIC/Northwestern Institute for Data, Econometrics, Algorithms, and Learning (online) 2020.
- Neural Information Processing Systems. Vancouver, BC, 2019.
- Emerging Challenges in Deep Learning Workshop. Simons Institute, Berkeley, 2019.
- Summer School in Probability. Pacific Institute for the Mathematical Sciences, Vancouver, BC, 2014.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- UC Davis, Department of Statistics
- Instructor, Stats 35B: Statistical Data Science II, Winter 2024.
- Instructor, Stats 250: Theoretical Foundations of Modern AI, Winter 2024.
- Organizer, Stats 290: Seminar in Statistics. Winter 2024.
- UCLA, Department of Statistics
- TA, Stats 100C: Linear Models, Spring 2020.
- TA, Stats 102C: Monte Carlo Methods, Fall 2019.
- TA, Stats 100B: Mathematical Statistics, Winter 2016.
- TA, Stats 100A: Probability Theory, Fall 2016.
- TA, Stats 10: Intro to Statistics, Summer 2016.

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES AND SKILLS

Python (including PyTorch & TensorFlow), R, Matlab.